<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<insight_products> 
  <insight_product id="230343"> 
    <ibmtext><![CDATA[ Technology Futures James Thompson CoPI
David Slater CoPI
Mainstreaming Complexity: Practical Decision-making in a Chaotic World
| 1 |
 
ICCS  23 July 2018
Approved for Public Release; 
Distribution Unlimited. Case Number 18-2452 What Is a Fractal?
Qualitative and Quantitative Definitions
Fractals vs. Multifractals
Algorithms for Multifractal Analysis
Fluctuation Analysis
Wavelets
Practical ApplicationsOK, but so What?
Forecasting
Anomaly Detection
Conclusions Next Steps Overview
 | 3 |
Fractals Objects That Do Not Simplify Under Magnification L-System:
Angle 120
Axiom F
F > F+FFF+F 
The Sierpinski Gasket
The Mandelbrot Set
Fractals are often created by simple iterative or recursive processes that lead to exceedingly complex objects
 The concept of a fractal is inherently related to dimension and measurement
In standard Euclidean geometry, as the measuring stick gets smaller (1/r), the quantity N(r) needed to cover the object grows according to the objects dimension and the measure of the object remains constant
| 4 |
But, Mathematically, What Do You Mean Do Not Simplify? Euclidean Object
1 x 1
Measuring stick .5 x .5
.5 x .5
.5 x .5
.5 x .5 11.5 x 200km = 2300km
28 x 100km = 2800km
70 x 50km = 3500km
Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coastline_paradox 
For fractal objects this relationship fails for integer dimensions
The net effect is that as the scale of the measuring stick decreases, the measure of the object grows without bound
To measure such objects, a fractional dimension is required and that dimension becomes the more important number
 1/r N(r)
 1 1
 2 4
 4 16
 8 64
 16 256
 
 1/r (1/r)2 Scale vs. Coverings
 4 Standard Brownian Motion is a simple fractal with dimension H = 0.5 
When treated as a time series this means the maximum and minimum are bounded by a cone proportional to time t raised to the power 0.5
Fractional Brownian Motion is also governed by a single value, but H is not restricted to 0.5
Values of H closer to 0.0 produce rougher paths, while values closer to 1.0 give smoother values
Thus H statistically quantifies the sample path
| 5 |
Time Series and Other Plots Can Also Be Fractal (i.e., Statistically Self-similar Across Scales) Source: http://cs.mcgill.ca/~tredda/brownian.html Standard Brownian Motion In multifractals, the points exhibiting a single value H are scattered throughout the object
In between are points exhibiting different values of H
At different moments q the fluctuations scale according to the scaling function (tau(q))
The full spectrum of power laws and a relative measure of their prevalence is known as the multifractal spectrum
The multifractal spectrum statistically quantifies the sample path of a multifractal
| 6 |
Multifractals Generalization of Fractals, One Value H Is Not Enough Apple Stock Price Since IPO
Days The multifractal spectrum is a relative measure of the number of fractal processes having the same smoothness (regularity)
A measure of the (local) regularity is the Holder exponent : For small , or The number of fractal processes with regularity scales as:
, or 
where is the multifractal spectrum
And we can relate to the scaling function via the Legendre transform
| 7 |
The Multifractal Spectrum Multifractal Spectrum: f(a) vs a
 Fluctuation or Wavelet Coefficients:
MF-DFA (or DMA) methods generally use the variance parameter estimated from polynomial regression at different scales
Wavelet methods equate the wavelet coefficients to the scaling function, tau(q)
Both approaches rely on mathematical variations of the multifractal formalism that equates something we can compute empirically to the scaling function
| 8 |
Algorithms for Extracting the Multifractal Spectrum A Multifractal Algorithm Taxonomy The data is iteratively segmented at different scales s
Polynomial regression is applied to each segment
The sum of variance from the regression of each segment F(s) is proportional to the scaling function tau(q)
| 9 |
Multifractal Detrended Fluctuation Analysis (MF-DFA) The continuous wavelet transform W(s, t) is a generalized time-frequency method using scales s and time translations t
| 10 |
Wavelets: A Brief Refresher Signal
Wavelet Transform
 10 | 11 |
Wavelets and Multifractals
If we sum up all the W(s, t) values raised to the power q we get something we can relate to the scaling function The sum is performed over lines L(s) that connect local maxima of the wavelet transform W(s, t) Signal: Apple Stock Price
Wavelet Transform | 12 |
Preliminary Results Accuracy of MF Spectrum Wavelet Leaders more often find a convex spectrum, but can vary wildly from one implementation to another
MF-DFA methods appear to fail more often than good Wavelet Leaders implementations, but are perhaps more accurate in the runs that do not fail
 Preliminary results match theoretical predictions:
MF-DFA computation time increases exponentially with length of the time series
Wavelet approaches vary depending on software implementation
Wavelet Leaders are fastest when implemented well
| 13 |
Algorithm Comparison Preliminary Results Computation Time Accuracy, as width of confidence interval, improves with more data
Results vary depending on software implementation
Wavelet Leaders is consistently better than other algorithms
| 14 |
Algorithm Comparison Preliminary Results Accuracy of the Spectrum Peak The degree of multifractality is related to the width of the spectrum
This is proportional to the 2nd derivative of tau(q)
Numerical estimations are prone to more error in general
Wavelet Leaders is again a consistently more accurate approach
| 15 |
Algorithm Comparison Preliminary Results Accuracy of the Spectrum Width Securities, options, and currencies often exhibit heavy tails and infinite auto-correlation
Calvet & Fisher construct a multifractal model that accurately mimics this complex behavior and allows for the construction of conditional probabilities of states over time
| 16 |
Applications: Forecasting and Large Deviations Calvet, Laurent, and Adlai Fisher. "Forecasting multifractal volatility." Journal of econometrics 105.1 (2001): 27-58. Shekatkar et al recently published in Nature a method for distinguishing healthy hearts from those on the verge of heart-failure using multifractals
The comparison can be performed with short-time ECG recordings enabling rapid diagnosis and response to failing hearts
Shekatkar, Snehal M., et al. "Detecting abnormality in heart dynamics from multifractal analysis of ECG signals." arXiv preprint arXiv:1705.00121 (2017).
 | 17 |
Applications: Anomaly Detection Original
Forgery Multi-fractal Analysis
Nontraditional image processing techniques have been used to quantify and measure various artwork features for:
Forgery detection
Restoration tracking
Dating Of particular interest is forgery detection based on texture analysis
Multifractal analysis methods are ideally suited for this application
The picture on the left is an original Bruegel drawing while the picture on the right is an imitation
The corresponding spectra (peak and width) are discernibly different P. Abry, S. Jaffard, and H. Wendt, Bruegals Drawings Under the Multifractal Microscope, ICASSP 2012, pp. 3909-3912 (2012) 
 On April Fools Day 2017, Reddit launched a social experiment in which they published a 1000x1000 canvas of pixels
Users could change a single pixel to one of 16 colors once every 5 to 20 minutes
Over 27 hours, 1 million+ users placed about 16 million pixels
Users collaborated in groups and creating bots was encouraged
| 18 |
Applications: Reddit Place https://www.youtube.com/embed/EDGpTJ6Pea0
 18 Reddit published a dataset of every pixel change over the entire experiment
As a test case for a large data set of images, we computed the Mulitfractal Spectrum for images every 90 seconds
Note the apparent stability in both the peak and the width after about time 500-600
| 19 |
Applications: Reddit Place Fractals are ubiquitous in nature and in the data we collect, but they remain esoteric and thus poorly understood
Algorithms for extracting multifractal properties from data have improved in both speed and accuracy
These improvements mean that multifractal analysis is poised to enter mainstream decision-making
A few practitioners are already employing multifractal analysis to great success
| 20 |
Conclusions ]]></ibmtext> 
  </insight_product>  
  <insight_product id="212344"> 
    <ibmtext><![CDATA[ PPT Presentation Corporate Overview Predictive Analytics for Mental Health Outcomes: A Case for Novel Applications of the Hedonometer* 
March 6, 2018 Presented by Josh Park and Lisa Tompkins-Brown
*Hedonometer developed in collaboration between University of Vermont and MITRE (Matt McMahon and Brian Tivnan)
Approved for Public Release. Distribution Unlimited. Case No. 18-0717. | # | 
 
Welcome to today's presentation. My name is 
With so many interesting presentations and exhibits going on right now I really appreciate your interest in exploring an emerging area of using advanced analytics to gain insight from large data sets to make informed decisions that ultimately lead to better health outcomes for our Nation. In today's talk we will talk about a tool that was developed in collaboration between MITRE and Academia (the University of Vermont) that measures happiness and how it has been and can be extended further to predict mental health outcomes in the general population and the Veteran community.
1 Discussion Overview
Introduction:
The Hedonometer is an instrument to remotely-sense emotional states and levels, in real time or post hoc. 
The Hedonometer provides an analytical platform to perform large-scale, sentiment analysis on many corpora in 10 global languages. 
Development:
The Hedonometer arose from a longstanding collaboration between the Computational StoryLab at the University of Vermont (UVM) and The MITRE Corporation.
Advancement: 
The team has explored various applications of the Hedonometer as an initial screening tool for detecting mental health outcomes in advance of clinical diagnoses.
Today: 
Our collaborative pursuit: applying the Hedonometer as an initial screening tool to identify those Veterans at greatest risk to attempt suicide. | # | 
 
The happiness measuring tool is called the Hedonometer. I'll conduct a demo Lisa will go over couple extensions of this tool Then I'll go over how it's being used for VA as part of our independent R&D efforts.
2 Discover new possibilities Create unexpected opportunities Lead 
by pioneering together with our sponsors and partners MITRE: Solving Problems for a Safer World 
Our work connects people and data to change the health market and reinvent the health experience | # | 
 
MITRE works in the public interest across finance, health, national security, cyber, aviation, and more to solve problems for a safer world. MITRE only operates FFRDCs currently 7 of them which cover most federal govt agencies. Federally funded research and development centers play an important role in working with government and industry to deliver game-changing solutions to complex challenges. FFRDCs must:
Meet a "special long-term research and development need" that cannot be met by in-house staff or traditional contractor resources. 
"Operate in the public interest with objectivity and independence" and "be free from organizational conflicts of interest."
Receive access to sensitive and proprietary data "beyond that which is common to the normal contractual relationship." This ensures that sponsoring organizations receive fully informed guidance that reflects an understanding of all critical points of view.
Form channels of expertise from multiple sources to advance government missions. These characteristics enable FFRDCs to act as long-term strategic partners with the government in such areas as:
Systems engineering and integration
Research and development
Study and analysis FFRDCs are an especially valuable resource when an agency confronts a challenge for which there is no obvious solution or a situation in which there are many viable solutions. In these cases, and independent analysis is required to determine which choice offers the agency the greatest benefits in terms of efficiency, effectiveness, and affordability. 3 Sponsor Engagement Data is the next level of innovation in health Mission-driven Objective insight Unique vantage point Technical know-how Pioneering together We believe in the power of partnership and trusted engagement to solve our nations toughest health problems, for a safer world. | # | 
 
Data is the new frontier. Using data in meaningful ways to drive mission success is MITREs strength and passion. Our work connects people and data to change the health market and reinvent the health experience. As Eric Schmidt said in his opening key note, data and information will drive the next wave of innovations through use of AI, machine learning, and predictive analytics to gain valuable insight so humans can make informed decisions. Like augmented reality, AI will augment human intelligence.
4 MITRE Partners with Academia to Discover Novel Way to Measure Public Sentiment
MITRE invests in partnership with University of Vermont (UVM) Resulting in the development of the Hedonometer
Analytical tool to perform large-scale sentiment analysis of social media content Extensions of Hedonometer to improve health outcomes for veterans
Early warning of emerging mental health issues like depression and PTSD
Veteran-ometer Application of Hedonometer specifically tuned for veterans | # | 
 
The Hedonometer was jointly developed in partnership with the University of Vermont. The experts at MITRE is Matt McMahon and Brian Tivnan. The tool in essence is a large-scale sentiment analysis of social media content. This can then be extended to measure a signal (MITREs roots lie in signal detection and processing radar, GPS, etc..). This signal can be detected and measured to determine an early warning system for mental health issues like depression and PTSD and help improve suicide prevention. We use a simple, fast method for measuring the happiness of texts that hinges on two key components: (1) human evaluations of the happiness of a set of individual words, and (2) a naive algorithm for scaling up from individual words to texts. we first use a pattern-matching script to extract the frequency of individual words in a given text. We then compute the weighted average level of happiness for the text neutral words averaging around 5
5 www.Hedonometer.org | # | 
 
Ideally, we open a browser here and navigate to the site: www.Hedonometer.org so we can explore some of the dynamics rather than rely on static image Expand and shift time window
Click on an event walk through components
Walk through tabs
Projects
Words Google Mechanical Turk (Mturk)
Press
Papers What we do: we look at the sentiment of populations, by applying the hedonometer algorithm to all tweets and then computing average happiness along with word shifts which explain changes in happiness over time. What we dont do: we cant legally filter and examine individual peoples tweets. So, for example we can look at all tweets that mention veterans, and examine the effect of public announcements by the VA on sentiment and word usage, but we cannot look at all tweets by an individual. 6 Hedonometer has been extensively vetted Additional Applications
Pattern of Life
Geography of Happiness
Lexicocalorimeter
Scientific Rigor of Hedonometer | # | 
 7 References: Scientific Foundation of Hedonometer
Several examples of peer-reviewed publications in top-tier, scientific journals Extension of Hedonometer beyond English to 10 global languages 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Human language reveals a universal positivity bias. Link to Publication
This paper won MITREs 2015 Best Paper competition. Link to MITRE Announcement
Recognized as #100 of Top Scientific Studies to Capture the Public Imagination in 2015. More here: https://www.altmetric.com/top100/2015/
Computational approach for efficient and scalable screening for depression via Instagram
EPJ Data Science, Instagram photos reveal predictive markers of depression. Link to publication
Recognized as #17 of Top Scientific Studies to Capture the Public Imagination in 2017. More here: https://www.altmetric.com/top100/2017/#list&article=10422853
Extension of efficient and scalable screening for depression and PTSD via Twitter
Natures Scientific Reports, Forecasting the onset and course of mental illness with Twitter data
Link to publication
Confirmed by controlled experiments, Hedonometer is without peer
EPJ Data Science, Sentiment analysis methods for understanding large-scale texts. 
Link to Publication Many more here: http://hedonometer.org/papers.html | # | 
 
Big picture: The results of our work and that of colleagues suggest that early-warning signs of emerging mental health issues like depression and PTSD can be observed in social media, even before any clinical diagnosis is made. The goal here is to build technology that identifies early warning signs of mental health problems, and connects individuals to a doctor sooner.
8 Predicting Depression from Instagram | # | 
 
Abstract: Using Instagram data from 166 individuals, we applied machine learning tools to successfully identify markers of depression. Statistical features were computationally extracted from 43,950 participant Instagram photos, using color analysis, metadata components, and algorithmic face detection. Resulting models outperformed general practitioners average unassisted diagnostic success rate for depression. These results held even when the analysis was restricted to posts made before depressed individuals were first diagnosed. Human ratings of photo attributes (happy, sad, etc.) were weaker predictors of depression, and were uncorrelated with computationally-generated features. These results suggest new avenues for early screening and detection of mental illness. We also employed a suite of supervised machine learning algorithms to estimate the predictive capacity of our models. We report prediction results only from the best-performing algorithm, a 100-tree Random Forests classifier. Depressed individuals in the study tended to post photos that were, on average, bluer, darker, & grayer than those posted by healthy individuals. Their photos also tended to have less faces than those posted by healthy participants. These markers are evident in the Instagram feeds of two UVM students (who did not participate in the study but agreed to provide their Instagram data for the purpose of raising awareness to mental health issues) and consistent with the psychological literature: depression has been shown to cause people to literally see the world through a colorless lens, and reduce their social activity. So while the results are not necessarily surprising, what is remarkable is that they hold even when we restrict model training to pictures posted prior to the date of diagnosis, demonstrating predictive skill. Furthermore, the model outperformed general practitioners average unassisted diagnostic success rate for depression. 9 Predicting Depression and PTSD from Twitter | # | 
 
In a companion study, we investigated predictors of depression & PTSD using twitter messages. Linguistic style, sentiment, and meta-data were used to train supervised learning algorithms. Resulting models successfully discriminated between depressed and healthy content, and compared favorably to general practitioners average success rates. Again, the results held even when the analysis was restricted to content posted before first depression diagnosis, suggesting that onset of depression and PTSD may be detectable several months prior to formal diagnosis. Machine learning models. We trained supervised machine learning classifiers to discriminate between affected and healthy sample members observations. Classifiers were trained on a randomly-selected 70% of total observations, and tested on the remaining 30%. Out of several candidate algorithms, a 1200-tree Random Forests classifier demonstrated best performance. 
We trained a two-state Hidden Markov Model (HMM) to detect differential changes between affected and healthy groups over time. 10 Pilot Study at University of Vermont (UVM): 
Predictors of Suicide Risk
Using social media to identify predictors of suicide risk Extending from two previous studies (Instagram and Twitter) Leveraging unique dataset from UVM hopstial 
1500 individuals who have died by suicide in VT, NH and northern NY
Names, cities, activity matched w/100 billion tweets in last decade | # | 
 
Big picture: The results of our work and that of colleagues suggest that early-warning signs of emerging mental health issues like depression and PTSD can be observed in social media, even before any clinical diagnosis is made. The goal here is to build technology that identifies early warning signs of mental health problems, and connects individuals to a doctor sooner. 11 Veteran ometer
Application of Hedonometer specifically tuned for veterans
Nearly ten years of Twitter data
Sentiment analysis for tweets containing veteran 
Relative count of tweets in the veteran set that contain opioids | # | 
 
Red: overall Hedonometer values Blue: veteran-ometer [ambient happiness for veterans] Green: relative count of of veteran-ometer tweets containing the word opioids Note: January 2017 was the date U.S. Secretary of Veterans Affairs Dr. David J. Shulkin announced that VA has begun publicly posting information on opioids dispensed from VA pharmacies, along with VAs strategies to prescribe these pain medications appropriately and safely. https://www.blogs.va.gov/VAntage/44376/va-becomes-first-hospital-system-release-opioid-prescribing-rates/ 
12 Veteran ometer
Zoom in to 2016-2018:
Dates Highlighted Jan 2, 2018
Most mentions of opioids
Veterans Day
Veterans Day
Oct 9, 2017
Memorial Day
Notes: We are working to add dates, events, VA press releases, and analysis around all the outlier datesextreme lows and highs in the data. | # | 
 
We are working to add dates, events, VA press releases, and analysis around all the outlier datesextreme lows and highs in the data.
13 Veteran ometer: Explaining differences with Word Shifts. Nov. 14, 2017 (Veterans Day)
Average Happiness: 6.40
Whats making this day happier than the previous seven days:
May 29, 2017 (Memorial Day)
Average Happiness: 6.05
Whats making this day happier than the previous seven days: October 9, 2017
Average Happiness: 5.14
Whats making this day sadder than the previous seven days: | # | 
 
The Happiness time series, along with the opioid frequency data, explain the What: What is average happiness in the veteran data on a given day?
Word Shifts explain the Why: Why is a particular day happy or sad relative do another day? 14 Potential Applications at VA
Assessing and understanding veteran sentiment
Leverage well established MITRE & UVM team of Data Scientists, Computational Social Scientists, and Psychiatrists
Quantifying and comparing analytics
Rigorous emphasis on quantifiable sentiment, insight into longitudinal changes over time 
Insight into the relevance of metadata relating location, TOD, relationships with other datasets, etc.
Proof of concept studies increasingly suggest there are linguistic & other behavioral predictors of state of mental health state, including suicidal.
Complete pilot study initiated at UVM Medical Center and potentially extend to VA, given a training set of VA data 
veterans w/wo mental health diagnosis who have died by suicide
veterans w/wo mental health diagnosis who have not attempted suicide
Build algorithm to identify predictors in classification task, validate on separate set of data. | # | 
 15 Thank you!
Josh Park
jpark@mitre.org Lisa Tompkins-Brown
ltompkins@mitre.org Technical POC: Matt McMahon
mcmahon@mitre.org | # | 
 16 Follow up To download a copy of this presentation, visit: https://health.mitre.org/himss18 Improving the 
Patient Experience
Follow us on social media: @MITREhealth | # | 
 17 |12| www.Hedonometer.org | # | 
 presentgeneralpractitionersunassisteddiagnosticaccuracyasreportedinMitchell,Vaze,and 
Rao(MVR)(24) .6 Results BothAlldataandPrediagnosismodelsweredecisivelysuperiortoanullmodel
.Alldatapredictorsweresignificantwith99%probability.57.5(KAll = 1 K 49.8) Pre = 1 
7 PrediagnosisandAlldataconfidencelevelswerelargelyidentical,withtwoexceptions: 
PrediagnosisBrightnessdecreasedto90%confidence,andPrediagnosispostingfrequency 
droppedto30%confidence,suggestinganullpredictivevalueinthelattercase. Increasedhue,alongwithdecreasedbrightnessandsaturation,predicteddepression.This 
meansthatphotospostedbydepressedindividualstendedtobebluer,darker,andgrayer(see 
Fig.2).ThemorecommentsInstagrampostsreceived,themorelikelytheywerepostedby 
depressedparticipants,buttheoppositewastrueforlikesreceived.IntheAlldatamodel,higher 
postingfrequencywasalsoassociatedwithdepression.Depressedparticipantsweremorelikely 
topostphotoswithfaces,buthadaloweraveragefacecountperphotographthanhealthy 
participants.Finally,depressedparticipantswerelesslikelytoapplyInstagramfilterstotheir 
postedphotos. Fig.2.MagnitudeanddirectionofregressioncoefficientsinAlldata(N=24,713)andPrediagnosis(N=18,513) models.Xaxisvaluesrepresenttheadjustmentinoddsofanobservationbelongingtodepressedindividuals,per 
standardizedunitincreaseofeachpredictivevariable.Oddsweregeneratedbyexponentiatinglogisticregression 
logoddscoefficients. 6Comparingpointestimatesofaccuracymetricsisnotastatisticallyrobustmeansofmodelcomparison.However, 
wefeltitwasmoremeaningfultoframeourfindingsinarealisticcontext,ratherthantobenchmarkagainstanaive 
modelthatsimplypredictedthemajorityclassforallobservations. 
7K abbreviatestheBayesFactorratiobetweenthesubscriptedmodelandanullmodel.SeeSIAppendixIVforK 
valuelegend. 8 presentgeneralpractitionersunassisteddiagnosticaccuracyasreportedinMitchell,Vaze,and 
Rao(MVR)(24) .6 Results BothAlldataandPrediagnosismodelsweredecisivelysuperiortoanullmodel
.Alldatapredictorsweresignificantwith99%probability.57.5(KAll = 1 K 49.8) Pre = 1 
7 PrediagnosisandAlldataconfidencelevelswerelargelyidentical,withtwoexceptions: 
PrediagnosisBrightnessdecreasedto90%confidence,andPrediagnosispostingfrequency 
droppedto30%confidence,suggestinganullpredictivevalueinthelattercase. Increasedhue,alongwithdecreasedbrightnessandsaturation,predicteddepression.This 
meansthatphotospostedbydepressedindividualstendedtobebluer,darker,andgrayer(see 
Fig.2).ThemorecommentsInstagrampostsreceived,themorelikelytheywerepostedby 
depressedparticipants,buttheoppositewastrueforlikesreceived.IntheAlldatamodel,higher 
postingfrequencywasalsoassociatedwithdepression.Depressedparticipantsweremorelikely 
topostphotoswithfaces,buthadaloweraveragefacecountperphotographthanhealthy 
participants.Finally,depressedparticipantswerelesslikelytoapplyInstagramfilterstotheir 
postedphotos. Fig.2.MagnitudeanddirectionofregressioncoefficientsinAlldata(N=24,713)andPrediagnosis(N=18,513) models.Xaxisvaluesrepresenttheadjustmentinoddsofanobservationbelongingtodepressedindividuals,per 
standardizedunitincreaseofeachpredictivevariable.Oddsweregeneratedbyexponentiatinglogisticregression 
logoddscoefficients. 6Comparingpointestimatesofaccuracymetricsisnotastatisticallyrobustmeansofmodelcomparison.However, 
wefeltitwasmoremeaningfultoframeourfindingsinarealisticcontext,ratherthantobenchmarkagainstanaive 
modelthatsimplypredictedthemajorityclassforallobservations. 
7K abbreviatestheBayesFactorratiobetweenthesubscriptedmodelandanullmodel.SeeSIAppendixIVforK 
valuelegend. 8 Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 13 Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 13 Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 13 Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 13 
Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays 
fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines 
representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, 
witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom 
traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple 
verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded 
regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial 
regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 
95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
13 
Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays 
fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines 
representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, 
witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom 
traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple 
verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded 
regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial 
regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 
95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
13 
Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays 
fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines 
representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, 
witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom 
traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple 
verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded 
regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial 
regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 
95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
13 
Figure2.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofdepression(N=74,990).Xaxisrepresentsdays 
fromdiagnosis.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Trendlines 
representcubicpolynomialregressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof14dayperiods, 
witherrorbarsindicating95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
Figure3.HiddenMarkovModelshowingprobabilityofPTSD(N=54,197).Xaxisrepresentsdaysfrom 
traumaevent.Healthydataareplottedfromaconsecutivetimespanofequivalentlength.Thepurple 
verticallineindicatesmeannumberofdaystoPTSDdiagnosis,posttrauma,andthepurpleshaded 
regionshowstheaverageperiodbetweentraumaanddiagnosis.Trendlinesrepresentcubicpolynomial 
regressionfitswith95%CIbands,pointsareaggregationsof30dayperiods,witherrorbarsindicating 
95%CIoncentraltendencyofdailyvalues. 
13 ]]></ibmtext> 
  </insight_product>  
  <insight_product id="202683">
    <ibmtext><![CDATA[ Schnitzer and Levin Page 1 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 *MITRE Approved for Public Release; Distribution Unlimited. Case Number 17-4670
1 http://www.motherjones.com/media/2013/05/robots-artificial-intelligence-jobs-automation/ The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology* By Jay J. Schnitzer and Peter L. Levin December 2017 By far the most important information known to mankind the human genome 
is stored in trillions of containers, inside billions of mobile agents, and dynamically 
refreshed millions of times per year. Not every update is perfect, and miniscule 
deviations can be healthy or self-destructive. But there are so inconceivably many 
copies that, taken in aggregate, new versions eventually break ground along a 
meandering path that began four thousand millennia ago. Evolution is indifferent 
to and unencumbered by quarterly reports to an owner; that class of 
experimental freedom has created the best innovation of all: life itself. Nature organized this chemical database into forty-six (twenty-three paired) units 
called chromosomes, each written in a deceptively simple four-letter alphabet. 
Our molecular-scale understanding of the story told in three billion cuneiforms of 
nucleic acid is only seventy years old, eyeblink short on the time scale it took to 
create its letter-by-letter assembly. Yet we can already connect some metabolic-
signal pathways to their genetic grammar. Until the last century we hardly knew this information existed. Fifty years ago we 
began to attach radioactive isotopes to small segments of chromosomes to see 
where they landed after mitosis. Today we have machines that allow us to actively 
read-and-write genes by the base-pair, almost like a modern word processor or 
software development environment. In other words, human-made hardware is now capable of changing the somatic 
software that runs us, like a computer autonomously downloading new apps it 
finds interesting, or willfully changing its operating system. Germline modification 
 the ability to permanently change DNA that is transmitted to offspring is 
coming soon. It will be inexpensive, reliable, and generally available. To understand how fast these changes will occur, consider Kevin Drums1 
animation that starkly demonstrates acceleration at Moores Law speed of 
change: doubling something every eighteen months. He pretended to fill Lake Schnitzer and Levin Page 2 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 2 https://www.technologyreview.com/s/427787/are-smart-phones-spreading-faster-than-any-technology-in-
human-history/
3 https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/speaking-of-science/wp/2017/11/29/cells-with-lab-made-dna-produce-
a-new-kind-of-protein-a-holy-grail-for-synthetic-biology/?utm_term=.ddef0ed220dc Michigan with water, starting with one fluid ounce, and then two fluid ounces a 
year and a half later, and then four fluid ounces three years after he started. After 
seven decades one can barely detect the results of such make-believe. Yet in only 
fifteen more years, the lake is full. Put in astronomical context: a little more than a 
century ago we were in the pre-Kitty Hawk days of heavier-than-air flight; two 
generations later we took giant leaps on the moon. Illuminating biological pathways for mischief or profit will occur faster still. The fusion of biotechnology and information science is new and uncharted. For 
most of history, information exchange, fake or not, depended upon physical 
access, which became sequentially easier with broadcast radio, then broadcast 
television, and most recently with the internet. The adoption of movable type for 
mechanical printing took almost exactly 400 years, from Bi Shengs invention to 
the Gutenberg Bible. The iPhone moved mainstream adoption of smartphones 
from 5% to 40% a typical metric of comparison in about four years.2 None of these advances remotely exploit the taproot of all information, literally 
encoded in our DNA. We can already manipulate cell-level outcomes by blocking 
certain functions that result in disease. Tomorrow we will change DNA itself to 
anthropogenically repair mutations that cause problems in the first place. The 
day after tomorrow we will manipulate molecularly bio-similar instructions 
outside of a living organism to produce new non-biological materials with 
properties we have never seen before, like those reported in November 2017.3 A genetic program of (only) three billion instructions can create a human baby in 
nine months. Now the underlying technology that reads the code-script, 
specifically the ribosomes (software developers would call these compilers) that 
assemble proteins one amino acid at a time, can be teleologically reverse 
engineered. Reflect, for example, on the power to genetically modify for strength, 
intellect, longevity, or control based on the current alphabet of 20 building blocks. 
Imagine synthetically extending the keyboard to include hundreds, thousands, or 
hundreds of thousands of new letters new amino acids for biological and 
non-biological applications. Truly we are at the incunabula stage the quiet Schnitzer and Levin Page 3 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 4 The Philadelphia Chromosome, by Jessica Wapner, published in 2013 by The Experiment, LLC interregnum between handwritten texts and mass-produced manuscripts in our 
ability to print molecular components whose attributes we-ourselves define. The public health implications of genetic de-coding are breathtaking. Prophylactic 
vaccinations against communicable disease coupled to curative therapies for 
cancer, diabetes, and heart disease mean that many of us, particularly in the 
developed world, will live longer, healthier, and physiologically safer lives. An 
individuals opportunity for creative contribution, including especially our 
collective scientific understanding, will grow exponentially. Few would want to turn the clock back to an age before anesthetics, x-rays, 
penicillin, or imatinib4. Fewer still can conceive the convergence of carbon-born 
ethics to silicon-born judgment. Developed-world innovation in artificial 
intelligence and biochemistry will exacerbate inequality, because it is 
institutionally and infrastructurally farther up the acceleration curve. The emerging miracles of modern biotechnology and biotech-inspired materials 
science conceal an existential threat to a fragile balance of international powers, 
and to our own national security. If not more thoughtfully debated on the global 
stage and controlled by multi-party agreement, our very existence is challenged 
by a single laboratory accident or ideologically-driven attack. There are now 
people in the world who perform scientific experiments that can lead to morally 
disturbing outcomes. There are now people in the world who aim to demolish the 
foundational institutions of modern society by any means possible. New systems, 
especially those that biomimick natural pathogens and cognitive synthesis, will far 
exceed our governments ability to control them. Riven enemies can too easily 
turn them against us and each other; ignorance and prejudice will fuel anger and 
violence. Scientific breakthroughs in biochemistry and microbiology will be further 
advanced by self-reinforcing capabilities of (irreversible) computer-aided 
decisions. For all the benefits of artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning 
(ML) and there are many the predictive power of these new technologies is 
imperfect, and their moral judgment and executive function is nonexistent. Dan Geer, In-Q-Tels chief information security officer, told us that, Our 
intervention in evolution is just more evolution, but at a faster clock rate. Schnitzer and Levin Page 4 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 5 https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/04/03/ai-versus-md Changes that depend on random perturbations take geologic time, including time 
to test for side effects. Changes that people design may have just as many 
unforeseen consequences, but the equilibria they punctuate are of much shorter 
duration. In other words, machine learning means self-modifying algorithms; it is 
impossible to ask them how they made their decisions, and their impact is quick 
and permanent. The problem, Geer explained, is that nations dont have 
geological time-scales to cull for fitness of their machine learning stock. What if 
the current generation of people becomes an experiment in evolution? Geoffrey Hinton has wisely observed5 that the algorithm can solve a case. It 
cannot build a case. In other words, AI and ML are great at deciphering the 
whats, wheres, and hows all questions that are essentially answered by 
extremely sophisticated pattern recognition but they cannot begin to 
understand why, which is the core of the human experience. AI and ML can help 
even-experienced professionals avoid poor choices, and they can suggest data-
driven hypotheses. But correlation is not causality, and neither can yet replace 
compassionate bedside manner, values-based judgement, or face-saving 
diplomatic nuance. AI and ML will continue to make marvelous contributions to 
diagnosis and classification, but they will not, in our opinion, and certainly not in 
the near term, be able to accurately harvest social sentiment or connect 
outcomes to social values. Even in a data drenched world, data scientists are still unable to predict the 
outcomes of plebiscites or the weather. And no computer would have anticipated 
the physical fatigue, psychological momentum, or miraculous catch that changed 
the otherwise prevenient outcome of the final quarter of Super Bowl LI. AI and ML 
reveal patterns; they cannot ask the right questions, detect insincere answers to 
national polls, or hypothesize Julian Edelmans hands. There are no silicon- (or 
even carbon-) based systems that can stop torture, stop ethnic cleansing, or 
better teach the irrefutable science of climate change. Today we are still untangling the engineering problem of cataloging proteomic 
outcomes to genetic codes, ribosomal assembly, and the restricted spectrum of 
natural components. Soon we will be able to create an editable biochemical code, 
with an expanded palette of man-made materials. Civil society must demand 
political leadership engage in open debate to determine if the outcomes are Schnitzer and Levin Page 5 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 6 https://science2017.globalchange.gov/downloads/CSSR2017_PRINT_Executive_Summary.pdf
7 https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/2016-09-05/automated-war desired or not, for whom, and why. On the one hand we need to agree and 
establish in international law acceptable scientific methods, ethical norms, and 
commercial standards; on the other hand, we need to recognize that some 
governments, and powerful individuals within those governments, will flout them 
anyway. There is no single agency in the US government, or any international body, that 
owns the bio threat. This leaves the US wide open to nefarious actors, just as it 
leaves the civilized world vulnerable to the malevolent, violent, and absent 
minded. The confluence of uncharted technical capability and poor prediction is 
especially serious now, because for the first time we have the capability not only 
to destroy ourselves on a nuclear scale, we might accidentally change the 
structure of our embedded software species-wide. The first experiments of so-
called germline embryos occurred in China. They were well intended. Soon 
enough they will be successful, and fall into the hands of less altruistic 
communities. The consequences are even more tragic and destabilizing than a 
suicide bomber who kills children (as incomprehensible as that is); genetic 
changes are heritable, persistent, and may be impossible to undo. Sonal Shah, the executive director of the Beeck Center for Social Impact and 
innovation at Georgetown University, said the convergence of AI with 
biotechnology is one of the most important social consideration of our times, on 
par with global warming. This is an important point, because from the scientific 
perspective, the case of carbon dioxide loading is well decided.6 General John R. 
Allen, who commanded coalition forces in Afghanistan, told us that the 
Department of Defense is investing in technologies that lower our carbon 
footprint and obviate climate change. We know how to model the security 
implications of increasing temperatures, he said, but the ethical considerations 
of autonomous systems deciding who to kill in a robot war are new and 
undecided. LaPoint and Levin made a similar point last year in these pages.7 There are plenty of examples of our collective inability to cooperate when the 
physical evidence is clear, for instance in contaminated water, depleted fishstock 
and inexorably rising tides. The existential threat of AI-driven biotechnology is 
abstract to most people, including highly educated policymakers of every color, Schnitzer and Levin Page 6 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 8 Peter L. Levin is a member of the board of this non-profit, non-partisan foundation. creed, culture, and continent. But knowhow, like the atmosphere, neither 
conforms to nor respects international borders. There are five decisions to make. First and foremost, we will implicitly choose whether or not to address these 
discussions openly, transparently, authentically, and democratically. We have 
already ceded a years-long head start to our friends, rivals, and enemies, primarily 
because of restrictions on stem-cell research. They are making dramatic progress 
in artificial intelligence and bio-engineering. So, first, we need to decide to decide. Second, assuming a more pro-active and deliberate process, the US government 
needs to dramatically increase funding into the overlapping disciplines of bio-
engineering and machine learning. There are, of course, undeniable benefits to 
an ageing society with a paucity of primary-care physicians. Superior pattern-
matching capabilities and front-line decision support to human clinicians will 
improve quality, lower costs, extend resources, and change lives for the better. 
Pedro Domingos of the University of Washington expects that AI will help screen 
drugs for toxicity much faster than human trials. He said, We know that some 
medicines may be poison to most people, but can save the lives of a small group 
of patients; we can use machine learning to safely reach those who will benefit. The most dire need for focused research is in the area of dementia and 
Alzheimers. George Vradenburg, founder of the non-profit USAgainstAlzheimers8 
estimates that the global cost to support Dementia victims already exceeds $1 
trillion, over 1% of global GDP, and is increasing at an accelerating rate. Ironically, 
nowhere is the need for advances in computer discovery more acute than human 
cognition and rational behavior. Third, we need to protect what we discover. We blithely live in the shoals of a 
relentless tsunami of breached personal data. This is a gigantic mistake. Our 
profligate attitude towards cybersecurity is going to migrate from personal 
inconvenience to economic intrusion, and from intrusion to physical incursion. We 
have lit up a fog-shrouded runway for our competitors and adversaries to land on; 
they will not need an invitation to take the next step. So much of societally 
beneficial innovation was born in the United States from satellite navigation to 
semiconductor design, and from advanced industrial materials to HIV therapies Schnitzer and Levin Page 7 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 9 The Master Algorithm, by Pedro Domingos, published in 2015 by Basic Books but we controlled, to a greater or lesser extent, when and how they were 
deployed. At this point not only do our rivals have a jump, they have an 
asymmetric advantage because they can see what we are, and are not, doing. Fourth, the United States needs to be keenly aware of the research and 
development efforts of other countries. Some intelligence gathering will 
inevitably fall on the shoulders of clandestine operations. Some requires more 
structured and pro-active engagement with globally-minded scientists from other 
nations, where academic collaboration and technical trust trump selfish 
commercial impulses (or clumsy friends) that may have detrimental or what we 
today perceive as detrimental effects on national security and economic 
competitiveness. Finally, the most difficult question of all: how much should we share? The 
convergence of scientific discovery (based on advances in the creation and 
construction of bio-mimicking processes), technological capability (based on 
advances in AI and ML), and ethical judgment (based on verifiable truthful and 
fact-based information) can lead to a richer, more peaceful world, or to horrible 
conflagration. There will be tremendous commercial advantage to the companies, 
and the nation-states that host or sponsor them, who master the science and 
technology of the 21st century. Left to their own devices, their human values and 
political goals will inevitably permeate not just consumer choice, but seats of 
government. Clearly there is a case for thoughtful dialog, for investment, for 
protection, and for nourishing communities of aligned and common interests. Domingos9 wrote, The real story of automation is not what it replaces but what it 
enables. Technologies that touch the genome shift the ethical, commercial, and 
global security paradigm in ways that are unprecedented in human history. 
However, unless and until we honestly, scientifically, and transparently approach 
the governance of our new-found powers, we need not fear cyborg domination 
any time soon, no, just the people who control them. Jay J. Schnitzer is Vice President and Chief Technology Officer of the MITRE 
Corporation, a not-for-profit company that operates multiple federally funded 
research and development centers. The author's affiliation with The MITRE Schnitzer and Levin Page 8 of 8
The Hope and Challenge of Synthetic Biology December 12, 2017 Corporation is provided for identification purposes only, and is not intended to 
convey or imply MITRE's concurrence with, or support for, the positions, opinions, 
or viewpoints expressed by the author. Peter L. Levin is a Non-Resident Fellow at the Beeck Center for Social Innovation 
and Impact at Georgetown University, and the CEO of Amida Technology 
Solutions. _top
 _GoBack ]]></ibmtext>
  </insight_product> 
</insight_products>
